The last of the microcytic anemias would be due to thalassemia.
Thalassemia is due to a decreased synthesis of globin chains.
That's what we find in a thalassemia,
that there's going to be decreased production of globin chains.
And so if there's decreased production of globin chains,
there's going to be decreased hemoglobin,
because globin would be down, so hemoglobin would be down,
and decreased hemoglobin would then result in a microcytic anemia
as per the paradigm that we've established.
So that's the general idea behind thalassemia.
I'd like to just stop here for a second
and remind you of a little bit of a technicality.
Notice that I'm saying that we're talking about
a decrease in synthesis of the globin chain.
So a decrease in synthesis or production of the amount of globin chain
is called thalassemia,
whereas you could have some diseases
in which there is an abnormality of the globin chain
after it's produced, for example, like in sickle cell anemia.
So in sickle cell anemia, you're producing globin chain.
However, the globin chain is defective.
So in thalassemia, the key is a decrease in synthesis
of the globin chain.
Thalassemia is usually due to an inherited mutation.
Prevalence of thalassemia is explained
by the fact that carriers are protected
against plasmodium falciparum malaria.
It's not enough to know that they're protected against malaria.
You need to know that they're protected
against plasmodium falciparum malaria.
Thalassemia is divided into alpha and beta thalassemia.
And so if there's a decrease in production of alpha chains,
we call that alpha thalassemia.
And if there's a decrease in production of beta chains,
then we call that beta thalassemia.
It's worth taking a moment here to remind ourselves
of the normal types of hemoglobin.
So the three normal types of hemoglobin usually seen
in a human being are fetal hemoglobin,
which is alpha 2, gamma 2, hemoglobin A,
which is alpha 2, beta 2, and then hemoglobin A2,
which is alpha 2, delta 2.
Of all of these hemoglobins, you can see
that there's a consistent use of alpha.
In one way, you can think of it as sort of the most important
of all of the globin chains.
And alpha is used by everybody.
Now I use that to remind me that there are actually
four copies of the alpha gene,
i.e. alpha is particularly important,
and so therefore there's a couple extra copies
of the alpha gene.
And so when you think about the genetics of the alpha chain,
it's important to know that the alpha chain,
that there are normally four alpha alleles
and that they're present on chromosome 16.
So basically this is what it looks like.
This is one copy of chromosome 16
and there'd be two genes here,
and then one copy of chromosome 16
and there'd be two genes here.
So it's important to know that there are four alleles
in alpha, four normal alpha alleles.
Now in alpha thalassemia,
the problem is going to be gene deletion.
This is also important to know.
You need to know that in alpha thalassemia,
the problem is gene deletion.
So what's going to happen is we're going to knock out genes,
and the knockout of the gene is then going to result
in clinical findings.
Now the first possibility would be that one gene is deleted.
So imagine again that we've got two copies of alpha
on this one chromosome and two alleles here
on the other chromosome.
If we knock out one alpha,
the patients are asymptomatic.
So that makes it easy because we don't have to worry
about one gene deleted.
Now what about if we knock out two genes?
Well, if we knock out two genes, for example, here and here,
and then here and here,
if we knock out two genes,
then the patients develop a mild anemia
with a slightly increased red blood cell count.
So there'll be a mild anemia
Not something that you have to worry about too much clinically.
Sometimes these patients don't even know
that they have a alpha thalassemia,
and not something that you have to worry too much about
on exams either.
But what is important for examination purposes,
and somewhat clinically,
is that really there's two possibilities
when you knock out two genes.
So it's possible that you could knock out both genes
on the same chromosome.
For example, both of them are here on this same chromosome.
We name that a cis deletion.
Cis means width.
Or it's possible that you could knock out
these on opposite chromosomes,
and that's called trans.
One possibility is cis,
and the other possibility is trans.
And the cis deletion is important
because the cis deletion is worse than the trans deletion.
So that's a question that could be asked.
Which is worse, the cis or the trans?
And the reason that the cis is worse
is because it's associated with an increased risk
of severe thalassemia in the offspring,
i.e. if a person has two genes deleted,
like this,
then it's possible that when they pass this chromosome,
they could pass both deleted copies.
And so if that person happens to receive
another bad copy from, let's say, a parent,
that would then result in the risk
for severe anemia in offspring.
So that's one important feature of the cis deletion.
The second important feature of the cis deletion
is that it's more commonly seen in Asians.
And some people say that
the higher rate of spontaneous abortions seen in Asia,
I guess one point to be aware of
is that in Asia,
there's a higher rate of spontaneous abortion,
and some believe that
it's actually due to the fact
that cis deletions are more common in Asia.
And by the way,
the trans deletions are more common in Africa.
Cis deletions are more common in Asia,
trans deletions are more common in Africa.
Patients who have three genes deleted,
they get a severe anemia.
Again, if you're going to knock out three genes,
you really don't have much choice.
You've got to knock out two-on-one chromosome,
and then the other one would be knocked out here.
What's then going to happen is that
as the patient develops in utero,
there really is no clinically detected problem.
Remember that the hemoglobin F,
which was the fetal hemoglobin,
is basically composed of alpha-2 and then gamma-2.
And so even though only one alpha gene is being expressed,
the presence of that one alpha gene
is sufficient enough for the fetus
to really avoid any problems.
When the fetus is born
and the patient begins to produce hemoglobin A
and hemoglobin A2,
that's going to increase the risk
of forming tetramers of beta chains.
Now, I guess to understand that,
you have to know that normally what happens
is sort of the alpha becomes a dimer
and then the beta becomes a dimer.
And so alpha-2 and beta-2 sort of join together
and then that forms hemoglobin.
However, if the patient doesn't have alpha,
then what will happen is
the betas will sort of join with another beta-2.
So the beta-2 will join with beta-2
and that would result in a tetramer of beta.
And the problem with that tetramer of beta
is that it damages the red blood cells.
Now, a tetramer of beta is called hemoglobin H.
That's important to know.
And hemoglobin H would be seen on electrophoresis
in alpha-thalassemia
in which three genes are deleted.
Now, if four genes are deleted,
then you've got a major problem
and it's going to express itself in the fetus
because remember that hemoglobin F,
which was the hemoglobin in the fetus,
contains alpha-2 and gamma-2.
And so if there's no alpha,
then gamma-2 is going to join with another gamma-2
and that's going to result in a tetramer of gamma
and the tetramer of gamma
would then damage the red blood cells.
And these patients, they die in utero.
And so this disease is lethal in utero.
It's also called hydrops fetalis.
Now, what would we see on hemoglobin electrophoresis?
We'd see hemoglobin BARTs.
And what is hemoglobin BARTs?
It is a tetramer of gamma chains.
So it represents tetramer of gamma chains.
All right, so that's alpha-thalassemia.
And now we go to beta-thalassemia.
And what's important to know about beta-thalassemia,
first of all, there are two beta genes.
One is on chromosome
and the other is on the second copy of the chromosome.
So there are two beta genes
and they're present on chromosome 11.
And perhaps particularly important
for this discussion and high yield
is that beta-thalassemia is due to gene mutations,
not deletions.
Remember, alpha-thalassemia, gene deletions.
Beta-thalassemia, gene mutations.
Now, these mutations can create
a variable production of beta chain.
If the mutation results in complete knockout
of the ability to produce beta chain,
then we call that beta null.
And if the mutation results
in decreased production of beta chain,
then we call that beta plus.
So these are the two possibilities.
Now, this creates a wide spectrum of disease.
So, for example, a patient could have beta,
a normal beta, and then beta plus.
Or a patient could have beta plus, beta plus.
Or a patient could have beta plus, beta null.
Or a patient could have beta null, beta null.
So there's a lot of permutations
of beta plus and beta null that could exist.
What we're going to do
is we're just going to focus on the extremes.
So one extreme, sort of the least severe extreme,
the mildest form of disease,
would be to have one normal beta,
and to have one beta plus,
where there was a slight decrease
in the production of beta.
This is called beta thalassemia minor.
It's usually asymptomatic.
And the patients may have
an increased red blood cell count.
They usually have a microcytic hypochromic anemia
with some target cells,
but again, they are asymptomatic.
Now, it's worth discussing for a moment here
what target cells are,
because this is the first time
that we're encountering a target cell.
So let's go back and remind ourselves
that the normal red blood cell
has a biconcave shape to it.
And the biconcave shape is such that
the edges here are thicker,
and they contain hemoglobin, right?
And the center is thinner,
and it contains less hemoglobin.
Now, when you look down
at the red blood cell on the microscope,
what you're actually seeing
is the red blood cell
with an area of central pallor.
This represents the central pallor.
And you see the edges,
which are full of hemoglobin.
So this is the normal image
that you see when you look down
on the microscope.
Now, a target cell, basically,
is when there is a bleb of membrane
that results.
And the bleb of membrane
allows for hemoglobin to build up
in that bleb,
which then creates a little bit of redness
within the center of the cell.
And so this is the target cell
will then give you this little dot of red
in the center of the area
where there should be central pallor.
So that's a target cell.
Now, when would we see a target cell?
Well, a target cell,
in order to see a target cell,
we need to have either
decrease in the cytoplasm
or increase in the amount of membrane.
Maybe the better way to understand this
would be to think about a basketball.
If you have a basketball
and you press on the surface of the basketball,
you're not going to be able
to indent the surface at all.
However, if you remove some air,
then you can potentially indent the surface
or you could create a bleb
of the surface of the basketball.
So in the same way,
what's happening in thalassemia
is that we're sort of reducing
the hemoglobin that's in the cytoplasm.
And by reducing the hemoglobin
that's in the cytoplasm,
it's like taking the air out of this ball,
which then creates the opportunity
to have a little excess membrane
to be able to produce this bleb
and form a target.
And here's an image of a target cell,
and it's exactly the way I drew it.
Here I'm highlighting the target cell for you.
Normally, this area in the center
should actually be an area of central pallor.
However, in this particular case,
you can clearly see that there is a target
sort of in the center there.
All right, now in this particular disease,
which again is beta thalassemia minor,
the key hemoglobin electrophoresis finding
is that there's going to be usually
an isolated increase in hemoglobin A2.
That's really the key finding.
So I would say when you think about
beta thalassemia major,
it's usually asymptomatic.
The patients have a microcytic hypochromic anemia
with target cells.
And then a key finding is an isolated
or an independent increase in hemoglobin A2.
And that's the key take-home message here.
The other extreme of disease would be
to knock out both beta chains completely,
so that it would be beta null, beta null.
And that's the most severe form of disease.
So it is the opposite extreme of beta thalassemia minor.
So in beta thalassemia major,
both beta chains are knocked out.
And so will there be a problem in the fetus?
The answer is no,
because fetal hemoglobin is actually alpha 2 gamma 2.
And so we don't need beta in the fetus,
and so there's no problem in the fetus.
However, as soon as the baby's born,
there'll be a demand to produce hemoglobin A,
and so these patients will present with severe anemia.
Now it takes a few months for the disease to develop,
and that's because the baby has fetal hemoglobin
floating around in the blood.
And so that fetal hemoglobin is temporarily protected.
So it's going to take a few months to develop.
Now what's going to happen,
because there are no beta chains, correct?
The beta chains are knocked out.
So now as alpha chains are produced,
the alpha chains will dimerize,
and then eventually you'll have alpha 2
looking to join beta 2,
but because there's no beta 2,
eventually alpha 2 will join alpha 2,
which will then produce tetramers of alpha.
And these alpha tetramers will precipitate,
and they'll damage the red blood cell.
When they damage the red blood cell,
that'll result in something called
ineffective erythropoiesis.
What that means is that as the red blood cells
are being made and alpha is being produced,
the alpha will actually precipitate
and damage the red blood cell
as they're being generated.
Another problem is that even if the red blood cell
does manage to get out of the bone marrow,
the spleen will recognize the abnormality
of this precipitated hemoglobin present
within the red blood cell
and will actually destroy the red blood cell
within the splenic macrophages.
And so this is the reason why these patients
have severe anemia.
Now because they have such severe anemia,
they get a massive erythroid hyperplasia.
What do I mean by that?
Well before you can understand
massive erythroid hyperplasia,
you need to recognize and remind yourself
that usually erythropoiesis and hematopoiesis,
in particular erythropoiesis,
occurs usually in the central axial skeleton.
Now when a baby's born,
erythropoiesis and hematopoiesis
will be present throughout most of the skeleton.
But as the patient grows,
usually the erythropoiesis is limited
to the central axial skeleton.
In this particular case,
because there's massive erythroid hyperplasia,
there's such severe anemia
that there's gonna be massive amounts
of erythropoietin being released by the kidney
in response to that anemia,
and that massive amounts of erythropoietin
will actually go to the bone marrow
and drive the bone marrow to undergo hyperplasia.
There'll actually be expansion of the hematopoiesis
into unique areas such as the skull
and the facial bones.
Now when there's expansion of hematopoiesis
into the skull,
that's gonna produce a classic crew cut appearance
on x-ray,
and so that's high yield to be familiar with.
And at the same time,
when there's expansion of hematopoiesis
into the facial bones,
that's gonna thicken the facial bones
and give the patient a chipmunk-like face.
What will also occur
is that these patients will get
extramedullary hematopoiesis
so that the liver and spleen
will also begin to produce red blood cells,
and obviously that would be extramedullary,
and that's gonna result in hepatosplenomegaly.
Another complication that can be seen in these patients
is a risk of aplastic crisis
with parvovirus B19 infection.
To understand this,
we have to remind ourselves
that these patients are dependent
on every single red blood cell
that's produced by the bone marrow
along with extramedullary hematopoiesis.
Now parvovirus B19
is a virus that infects erythroid precursors,
and when it infects erythroid precursors,
it shuts them down.
Normally, it's a self-limited infection,
and it'll last for a week or two weeks,
and in most patients, in the normal patient,
it wouldn't really have any effect
because, for example, you and I
have a tremendous reserve in our bone marrow,
and we can afford to shut down
production of red blood cells for a week or two.
However, these patients,
the beta-thalassemia major patients,
are so dependent on every single
red blood cell that they produce
that they can't risk shut down even for a day.
And so parvovirus B19 in these patients
would create an aplastic crisis,
and so that's an important thing
to be familiar with.
Here's a classic image
that shows up on examinations.
This is the crew-cut appearance of the skull,
and again, it's indicative
of massive expansion of hematopoiesis
into regions where hematopoiesis
would not normally occur within the bone.
It's not uncommon for these patients
to be dependent on transfusions,
and so chronic transfusions are often necessary.
Now, this will lead to a risk
for secondary hemochromatosis,
and what do we mean by that?
Well, basically, remember that
every time you're giving a bag of blood,
you're actually giving a bag of iron
because those red blood cells
are going to be broken down,
and that iron is now going to be present
within the body.
Remember that the body really has no way
of getting rid of iron,
so every bag of blood is basically a bag of iron,
and as iron begins to build up within the tissues,
eventually the complication
of having excess iron in tissues
is called hemochromatosis,
and that's a disease we'll talk about later
in the liver lectures.
However, at this point,
you should recognize that it's secondary
because it's secondary due to chronic transfusions.
On blood smear,
these patients will have
a microcytic hypochromic anemia
with target cells,
and I've already explained that.
At the same time,
there will be some nucleated red blood cells.
Now, normally,
our red blood cells do not have nuclei,
and we remove those nuclei
before the red blood cells
can go out into the blood.
However, if red blood cells
are made in an abnormal location,
for example, the spleen or the liver,
as would occur in this disease,
some of the nucleated red blood cells
can actually escape out into the blood,
and so we might see circulating nucleated red blood cells
in this particular disease.
On electrophoresis,
the key finding,
no hemoglobin A.
The only hemoglobins that the patient will have
are hemoglobin A2,
and again,
A2 is made up of alpha 2 and delta 2,
and so there's no beta needed to make A2,
and they'll have hemoglobin F,
and hemoglobin F is alpha 2 and gamma 2,
and again,
there's no need for beta,
so the key finding would be no hemoglobin A.
And that concludes our discussion
of microcytic anemias.
The next section will deal with macrocytic anemia.